Guide to the Martin Wohl papers, 1919-2000s
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Martin Wohl papers
1919-2000s
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Martin Wohl, 1930-2009
C0174
7.25 linear ft.; 10 boxes
Consists of information on urban transportation and traffic engineering subjects in reports (some co-written by Wohl), his degree work (bachelor's and master's theses, Ph.D. dissertation), interviews with Wohl, clippings, and correspondence, including letters to magazine and newspaper editors.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Damian Kulash in 2009.
Biographical Information
Born in 1930 in Greensboro, North Carolina, Martin Wohl studied and wrote about transportation economics for more than 30 years. He received a master's degree in engineering from MIT in 1960 and a doctorate in engineering from the University of California at Berkeley in 1966. He worked in the Department of Commerce during the Kennedy Administration and taught at Harvard University for two years following that. He later returned to Washington, D.C., to head the transportation studies department at the Urban Institute in 1969, and in 1972, he accepted a faculty position at Carnegie Mellon University. He is most recognized for "The Transportation Problem" (1965), the book he co-authored with John R. Meyer and John F. Kain. He died in 2009 at his home in Fairfax City, Virginia.
Scope and Content
This collections contains writings, records, photos, and scrapbooks of one of the founders of transportation economics, Martin Wohl. The majority of the collection focuses on Wohl's work as a transportation economist, but the records and photographs depict Wohl and his family and friends throughout his life.
The first series contains essays, newspaper articles, journal articles, books, and reviews surrounding Wohl's work in urban transportation and traffic engineering (written both by and about Wohl). Also in this series are his records, including degree work (bachelor's and master's theses, Ph.D. dissertation), interviews with Wohl, clippings, and correspondence, including letters to magazine and newspaper editors. Much of the professional correspondence contains information on the publication of his books (including copyrights), and there are also files with copies of reviews of his books The Urban Transportation Problem and Traffics Systems Analysis. Cities analyzed in the collection include Washington, D.C., San Francisco, Boston, Pittsburgh, and Los Angeles. The second series consists of photographs, mostly black and white snapshots. The subjects include family, military service, West Point, and Cambridge, and Wohl himself. The third collection contains two unbound scrapbooks that contain photographs and emphemra from Wohl's life mostly from the 1930s through the 1960s.
Arrangement
Organized into three series.
Series 1: Subject Files, 1958-1993 (Box 1-7)
Series 2: Photographs, 1919-2000s (Box 8)
Series 3: Scrapbooks, 1930s-1960s (Box 9-10)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds many other.
Index Terms
Persons:
Wohl, Martin.
Subjects:
Local transit--United States.; Transportation engineering--United States.; Transportation--United States--Planning.
Document Types:
Photographic prints.; Scrapbooks.
Contents List
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1958-1993
  Contains essays, newspaper articles, journal articles, books, and reviews surrounding Wohl's work in urban transportation and traffic engineering (written both by and about Wohl).
  - 20th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Conference of AAA motor Clubs, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Study for the Improvement of Traffic Conditions At the Boston University Bridge (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Applications of Simulation to Highway Traffic Design, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Applications of Symbolic Models and Simulation In Traffic Engineering, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards/Certifications, 1946-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The Society of the Sigma Chi,Chi Epsilon Fraternity, The National Society of Professional Engineers, Massachusetts Registered Professional Engineer, MIT B.S. and M.S. in Civil Engineering, MIT Education Council Member, MIT Sustaining Fellow Founding Life Member
  - Clippings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Jan-Feb-March
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    April
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    May-June-July-August
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Sept-Oct-Nov-Dec
  - Clippings, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, 1978-1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Copyright, 1958-1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Development Of A rational For Transportation Investment, Preliminary Notes On Advanced Highway Engineering, Urban Transportation Myths, Vehicle Speeds and Volumes Using Sonne Stereo Continuous Strip Photography
  - Department of Transportation/Commerce Papers, 1963-1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Development of Rationale for Transportation Investment, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Dr. Martin Wohl's Records, 1947-1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Essays [1 of 2], 1966-1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Essays [2 of 2], 1966-1977 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Evaluation of the US National Capital Transportation Agency Report (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Harvard Transportation Research Program Papers [1 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Harvard Transportation Research Program Papers [2 of 2], 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - From Private to Public Transit, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Improvement of Bus Service Between Washington and Portions of Virginia, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Institute of Traffic Engineers, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Joint Highway Research Project, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Letters to Dr. Wohl, 1961-1977 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Letters to Editors, 1966-1987 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Magazines, 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - McGraw-Hill (Traffic System Analysis), 1960-1971 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Meyer-Kain-Wohl Reviews and Comments, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Obituaries, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Policy Proposals, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    "Assessing Prospects of Current Transport Proposals", "Analysis of Transportation Investment and Use", "Equity Considerations of Urban Transportation Planning", "Current mass-transit proposals: Answer to our commuter problems?", "Thoughts About Congestion Toll Pricing For Public Transport Facilities"
  - Preliminary notes on Advanced Highway Engineering, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Pricing As It Relates to Investment Planning, Financing, and Highway Cost Allocation (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Private and Unregulated Carriage, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Public Transport Investment and Policy Analysis, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Rand Corporation Memorandums, 1963-1969 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    "Alcohol and Traffic Accidents", "Safety In Transportation: The Role of Government, Law, and Insurance", "Emergency Medical Care and Traffic Fatalities", "Vehicle Safety: Why The Market Did Not Encourage It and How It might Be made To Do So", "Modeling the Traffic Safety System, Recent Land-Use Trends In Forty Eight Large American Cities", "A Conceptual Framework for Evaluating Traffic Safety System Measures", "Putting The Analysis and Evaluation Of Traffic Safety Measure Into Perspective"
  - Rand Corporation Papers, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    "Another View of Transport System Analysis", "Notes on Transient Queuing Behavior, Capacity Restraint Functions and Their Relationship to Travel Forecasting" (2 copies), "An Economic Re-Evaluation Of The Proposed Los Angeles Rapid Transit System", "A Not So Common View of the Ground Transportation Problem", "New Directions For Passenger Demand Analysis and Forecasting"
  - Route 128 Study, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - The Urban Transportation Problem, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Technology and urban Transportation, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Traffic Systems Analysis for Engineers and Planners, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Traffic System Analysis (Reviews and Comments), 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Transportation Research Board, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Urban Institute Reprints, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    "Congestion Toll Pricing For Public Transport Facilities", "Assessing The Prospects of Current Transit Proposals" (2 copies), A Methodology For Forecasting Peak and Off-Peak Travel Volumes" (2 Copies), "Urban transport We Could Really Use", "The Urban Transportation Problem: A Brief Analysis of Our Objectives and the Prospects for Current Proposals", "The Practicalities of Determining Marginal Delay Times and Costs" (2 Copies), "What Kind of Transport Will the Urban Public Use - Today and Tomorrow?", "The Junk Vehicle Problem: Some Initial Thoughts"
  - Urban Institute Working Papers, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    "Towards Better Public Transport Financing, Pricing and Investment Decisions", "What Kind of Transport Will The Urban Public Use - Today and Tomorrow?", "A Methodology For Forecasting Peak and Off-Peak Travel Volumes"
  - Wohl Hendrickson Book Reviews, 1984-1993 (Box 7, Folder 60)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1919-2000s
  Consists of photographs, mostly black and white snapshots. The subjects include family, military service, West Point, and Cambridge, and Wohl himself.
  - 5th MIT Class Reunion, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes marked overlay labeled: "Each dot = 1 Male classmate (Bob Anslow was not included)"
  - Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Martin Wohl, 1923-2000s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Friends and Family, 1919-2000s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Anne Wolf, Stanley S. Wohl,
  - Hutzler Calendar, Annapolis, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - West Point, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Scrapbooks, 1930s-1960s
  Contains two unbound scrapbooks that contain photographs and emphemra from Wohl's life mostly from the 1930s through the 1960s
  - Scrapbook, 1930s-1960s (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1930s-1960s (Box 2)